A Guide to the Papers of Ernest Hemingway, 1925-1961, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Ernest Hemingway, 1925-1961, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6250, etc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
6250: Deposit, March 19, 1960; Gift, April 5, 1991 6250-a: Deposit, April 16, 1960; 6250-b: Purchase, December 11, 1963 6250-c: Deposit, January 21, 1964 6250-d: Archival transfer, May 9, 1966 6250-e: Deposit, September 29, 1971 6250-f: Purchase, December 6, 1972 6250-g: Purchase, December 12, 1972 6250-h: Purchase, January 3, 1973 6250-i: Gift, October 9, 1980 6250-j: Gift, February 23, 1984 6250-k: Gift, December 11, 1984 6250-l: Purchase, February 19, 1985 6250-m: Purchase, June 12, 1985 6250-n: Purchase, April 22, 1991 6250-o: Archival transfer, n.d. 6250-p: Purchase, n.d. 6250-q: Purchase, December 17, 1992 6250-r: Archival transfer, February 7, 1997 6250-s: Purchase, April 16, 1996 6250-t: Transfer, June 11, 1997 6250-u: Archival transfer, September 14, 1998 6250-v: Purchase, February 27, 2001 6250-w: Purchase, March 25, 2002 6250-x: Purchase, May 28, 2003 6250-y: Purchase, November 10, 2005 6250-z: Purchase, November 14, 2008 6250-aa: Purchase, November 28, 2008 6250-ab: Purchase, December 22, 2008 6250-ac: Purchase, April 7, 2010 6250-ad: Purchase, March 7, 2011 10247: Deposit for copying by Museum of Ogunquit, Ogunquit, ME,1977 October 13
Biographical/Historical Information
Ernest Hemingway (July 21, 1899-July 2, 1961)was an American novelist, short-story writer and journalist. His distinctive writing style is characterized by economy and understatement and had a significant influence on the development of twentieth century fiction. Hemingway's stoic protagonists are often seen as projections of his own character- men who must show grace under pressure. Many of his works are considered classics in the canon of American literature.
Hemingway, nicknamed "Papa," was part of the 1920s expatriate community in Paris, as described in his memoir A Moveable Feast, and was known as part of "the Lost Generation," a name he popularized. He led a turbulent social life, was married four times, and allegedly had various romantic relationships during his lifetime. Hemingway received the Pulitzer Prize in 1953 for The Old Man and the Sea. He received the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1954. In 1961, at age 61, he committed suicide in Idaho.
Scope and Content
The collection contains manuscripts of essays, poems, and short stories including "The Dangerous Summer"; a clean carbon of Green Hills of Africa typed by Jane Armstrong; and galley proofs of The Old Man and the Sea, A Farewell to Arms, and Death in the Afternoon.
The collection Also contains the manuscript of a dramatization of The Snows of Kilimanjaro; the manuscript of Peter Viertel's screenplay of The Sun Also Rises with Hemingway's extensive autograph corrections, together with the mimeographed first draft and final script; the transcript of an interview with students in Hailey, Idaho; and page proofs of the original version of Papa Hemingway.
In letters to Ernest Walsh and Ethel Moorhead, Hemingway chiefly discusses publication of The Undefeated including printing problems with This Quarter. He Also discusses writing The Sun Also Rises, The Fall of Herriot's Government a Tyrolean Walking Tour, and mentions Sylvia Beach, H. L. Mencken, Robert McAlmon, Ezra Pound, Gertrude Stein, and the current French and Italian governments.
Correspondence with Horace Liveright discusses the publication of In our time, including the replacement of a censorable story, sales potential and possibility of favorable reviews. Letters Also discuss The torrents of spring and its satirization of Sherwood Anderson, and mention James Joyce's Finnegan's Wake, an appearance in an anthology, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Louis Bromfield, and Ralph Barton.
Correspondence between Ralph Ingersoll and Joseph Losey discusses a production of The fifth column.
Letters to A. E. Hotchner discuss work for Cosmopolitan magazine, Italy after World War II, fishing, hunting, bull-fighting and travels in Spain, Across the River and into the Trees, The Old Man and the Sea, Hotchner's adaptations of Hemingway's work for the theater, and the writing of and events and people in The dangerous summer including matadors Antonio Ordez and Luis Miguel Domingun?. There are comments on Ingrid Bergman, Malcolm Cowley, Robert Flaherty, Joe Di Maggio and baseball, Ava Gardner, John O'Hara, Ted Patrick, Eric Sevareid, Gary Cooper, Valerie Danby-Smith, Alfred Rice, cock-fighting, sailing, the 1948 election, Korean War, Cuban revolution, Peter Buckley's Bullfight, business arrangements, health and sobriety, and family.
Several letters from Mary Hemingway to Hotchner discuss Hemingway's health and writing as well as her own writing. Individual letters mention hunting in Idaho, Leonard Bernstein, the Cuban revolution, bull fighting and Death in the Afternoon.
Letters to Bronisaw Zieliksi discuss shooting in Idaho, royalties to establish a prize in Poland, health, the Cuban Revolution, short story Cross Roads, love of Spain, translations and Zieliksi's PEN prize.
Correspondence with Jane and Richard Armstrong concerns the typing of Green Hills of Africa. The letters Also mention John and Katy Dos Passos, Max Perkins, requested photographs of Carlos Gutirrez rigging baits, work on Cuba, H. L. Woodward, and response of old timers in Kenya to Green Hills.
Additional letters discuss James Joyce, life in Paris, discrepancies between views of critics and readers, bullfighters, being struck by lightning, John Hemingway's World War II service, and editorial decisions about Farewell to Arms. He Also responds to collectors, and lists the best three books of 1932. People mentioned include Sidney Franklin, Samuel Goldwyn, and Archibald MacLeish.
Additional correspondents include Merle Armitage, Campbell Becket, Robert Bridges, Marlene Dietrich, Herbert Gorman, Gregory H. Hemingway, Patrick Hemingway, R. W. Stallman, Frank Stanton, Charles B. Strauss, and Ernest Walsh.
The collection Also contains contracts; recordings of readings by Hemingway; a water-color portrait of Hemingway; photographs of Hemingway, Mary Hemingway and bullfights, including nine by by Robert Capa, and miscellaneous photographs from magazines; and a record album A portrait in sound of Ernest Hemingway.
Arrangement
The Papers of Ernest Hemingway are arranged in five series. Series I: Literary Manuscripts, is arranged alphabetically by title. Series II: Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's surname and sub-arranged chronologically. Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Series IV: Photographs, Slides and Portraits are arranged chronologically. Series V: Audio and Video Recordings.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - Across the Board, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs carbon copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:1)
    6250-f
  - The Art of the Short Story, by Ernest Hemingway 1959 June, TMs negative photocopy, 13 pp. on 13 l. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Black Ass at the Cross Roads, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs positive photocopy, 26 pp. on 26 l. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - The Bubble Illusion, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs positive photocopy, 12 pp. on 12 l. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Country Poem with Little Country, by Ernest Hemingway [1949 December 22], TMs carbon copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 1-100. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 101-200. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 201-300. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 301-400. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 401-500. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 501-600. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway [1960], TMs carbon with autograph corrections, pp. 601-699. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - The Dangerous Summer, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - The Dangerous Summer, notes by Ernest Hemingway [1960], ANs, 30 pp. on 30 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - The Dangerous Summer, background notes"> 1960 August 15-16, TMs, 8 pp. on 8 l. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - First Poem to Mary in London and Poem to Mary (second poem), by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs negative photostat, 10 pp. on 10 l. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Includes one paragraph letter to Mary [Hemingway] at conclusion of poem, with location and date ("Ritz Hotel, Paris September, 1944") scratched through. 6250-f
  - The Green Hills of Africa, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., AMs, ca. 491 pp. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Holograph pages in ink and pencil, representing the text before transcription to typescript. There is no page 78 in the manuscript. This was a numbering mistake on Hemingway's part. The typing job was done by Jane Armstrong (wife of the journalist-photographer Richard Armstrong) in Cuba, as Hemingway explains in his letter fragment to [Charles Scribner] that accompanies the manuscript, attesting to its authenticity. He says he wanted to give Jane Armstrong something that would be worth money someday as thanks for help; hence, her possession of the manuscript. He urges Scribner's to pay Mrs. Armstrong's daughter (who is offering the manuscript for sale) "all you can for it to take your percentage" on resale. SEE SLIPCASE 6250-a
  - The Green Hills of Africa, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs, ca. 323 pp. (Box-folder 1:18)
    There are many differences between this typescript and what finally appeared in the published version. And the changes are throughout. Generally Hemingway was much less temperate in his language. As an example, he is more scathing and more detailed in his attacks on Gertrude Stein.
    Jane Armstrong used two different typewriters during her typing of the book. One of the typefaces is pica, ten characters to the inch, and the other is a unique, larger type, about nine characters to the inch. SEE SLIPCASE 6250-s
  - The Littlest Present, by Ernest Hemingway 1957 July 21, TMs, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - The Old Man and the Sea, by Ernest Hemingway 1952, Advanced uncorrected galley proofs, 17 pp. on 17 l. (Box-folder 1:20)
    For the first publication of this work in Life magazine. OS tray 124. 6250-o
  - Papa Hemingway, by A. E. Hotchner"> 1966, TMsS, 1 volume. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - A Room on the Garden Side, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs positive photostat, 11 pp. on 11 l. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - The Sea Chase, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs photocopy, pp. 1 - 104. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Unpublished manuscript. 6250-f
  - The Sea Chase, by Ernest Hemingway> n.d., TMs photocopy, pp. 105 - 218. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - The Shot, by Ernest Hemingway [1955], TMsS, 8 pp. on 8 l. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - The Snows of Kilimanjaro, screenplay by Ernest Hemingway 1955 July 5, TMs with signed autograph corrections, 30 pp. on 30 l. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - The Sun Also Rises, by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs with autograph corrections, 326 pp. (Box-folder 2:7)
    After The Sun Also Rises was set in galley proofs at Scribner's, F. Scott Fitzgerald read a carbon copy and suggested that the first two chapters be omitted and that the novel begin with the opening of chapter three, when Jake Barnes meets the prostitute Georgette. Hemingway took Fitzgerald's advice partially and deleted most of the first two chapters, about 3,500 words beginning with the introduction of Robert Cohn. After the deletion, Hemingway tried several times to insert a beginning that explained the disappearance of the opening material. He eventually abandoned this effort because "by referring to the cut chapters it merely capsulizes the faults of those chapters." After the very late revision suggested by Fitzgerald, the novel was published October 1926 as it stands today. This is the printer's setting copy of The Sun Also Rises which, in the original state, contained the two opening chapters excised after the book was already in galleys. This typescript, which had been in the Louis H. Cohn Collection, was presented to the University of Virginia Library in March 1977 by Mrs. Louis H. Cohn as a memorial to her late husband. SEE SLIPCASE 10208,10209
  - The Sun Also Rises, by Ernest Hemingway: transcript of Chapter 1 by Stephen Railton"> 2001, TMs, 10 pp. on 10 l. with computer disk. (Box-folder 2:8)
    10208-a
  - The Sun Also Rises, screenplay (first draft) by Peter Viertel"> 1956 June 8, TMs, 157 pp. (Box-folder 2:9)
    6250-p
  - The Sun Also Rises, screenplay by Peter Viertel"> 1956 June 25, TMs with autograph corrections, 141 pp. (Box-folder 2:10)
    SEE SLIPCASE 6250-q
  - The Sun Also Rises, screenplay (final draft) by Peter Viertel"> 1957 February 20, 143 pp. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - There was a cat... by Ernest Hemingway n.d., TMs carbon, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:12)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - [Jane Armstrong] to Ernest [Hemingway], [1935?] January 4, TL, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Armstrong apologizes for not editing Hemingway's manuscript as too many things distracted her. The Dos Passos' are visiting. 6250-s
  - [Jane and Richard Armstrong] to Ernest [Hemingway], [1935?] January 11, TL, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Returns the manuscript they were editing to Hemingway, and give praise to the work: "it was a great experience: watching it unfold, the vibrant Africa I knew it must be, the country you're homesick for though you've never seen." 6250-s
  - Jane P. Armstrong to Ernest Hemingway, 1945 April 5, TL, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Compares the images of Africa which she has seen first hand to the images from Hemingway's book [The Green Hills of Africa]. Only six months into a two-year term in Kenya and does not know what is happening in the world. 6250-s
  - [Louis H.?] Cohn to C[lifton] W[aller] Barrett, [1960] July 4, APCS, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:4)
    A photograph of Mount Kilimanjaro on front of postcard that Cohn thought Barrett would like to add to Hemingway collection. 6250-b
  - [Valerie] Danby-Smith to [Robert A.] Wilson, 1960 March 19, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Thanks for letter. Hemingway will sign Wilson's books next time he is in New York. 6250-d
  - Phyllis Danielson to David A. Randall, 1947 July 25, TLS photocopy, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Asks Randall that when he sells the Hemingway manuscript to deposit check under the name of Jane P. Armstrong and send it to her in the American Consulate in New Zealand. Original letter and envelope in autograph manuscript of The Green Hills of Africa. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925] March 27, TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Enclosed is a big bullfight story [The Undefeated]. It was turned down by every reputable and disreputable magazine in the States. Wrote his guts out. Hopes he will like it. Tried to get quality of the In Our Time action into a long story. Sent proofs. Write regarding delay in getting proofs. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925 March 31], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:8)
    All proofs sent to him. Will send copy of cover as soon as available. Tells reasons for delay at Clark"s: water cut off which caused printing problems for This Quarter. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to Horace Liveright, 1925 March 31, TL copy, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:9)
    Enclosed signed contract, and new story to replace the one he is eliminating as censorable. Stipulates no alterations of words are to be made without his approval. Good news that it is no longer necessary to eliminate "the fine old word 'son of a bitch.'" Thinks book has a good gambling chance to sell. Classic examples of really fine book that could not sell: E. E. Cummings' The Enormous Room. Hemingway's book will be praised by highbrows and can be read by lowbrows. Has a good 3/1 chance. The new story makes a better book: it's almost the best he's ever written. He is eliminating the second story, Up in Michigan, the next three move up one place and the new story, The Battler, takes place of The Three Day Blow. Pleased to be published by Boni & Liveright. Hopes he will become a property. 6250
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernesto della Walsha [Ernest Walsh], [ca. 1925 March], TLS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:10)
    Forgot to mention Gertrude Stein's stuff. Thinks it is splendid. Complains about slow printing of This Quarter by Clarke. Suggests Bill Smith be hired to expedite business of publication, so he can be relieved of job. Hasn't written a thing since going down to Clarke's and has to get to work on his own book. He is miserable and ugly if not creating. Concludes letter with note to [Ethel] Moorhead, thanking her for check that will pay rent, buy groceries, etc. Glad she thinks it a great story. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925?] April 1, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 3:11)
    Went to Clarke with corrected proofs of [This Quarter]. Gives details of changes to be made. Criticizes Walsh's statement that Ezra Pound was a bad judge of wine, food and women, but a good judge of furniture, boys and sculpture. Sounds as if Ezra were a "bugger." Afraid people will get the wrong idea. Change to "young poets or artists"? Asks Walsh questions on how to set up publication, and other business details. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925 April 10], TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:12)
    Review [This Quarter] is on press and being printed. Spine reads Spring, not April. Better as a quarterly. Clarke's press broken; 250 pages too big for his equipment. Says [Êdouard] Herriot government [of France] having "a hell of a time." Expected to fall Wednesday but no government ever did anything on time. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925 April 12], TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:13)
    [This Quarter] well into printing. Going to be a damned fine review. Nothing can stop it except rats eating rollers. Will have by April 23. Government fell as expected, but franc stays up. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], 1925 April 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:14)
    Mrs. Moorhead gave them a couple of bottles of damned fine wine. Walsh seems suspicious that Hemingway is inventing ways to do him out of money. He has strong idea people are out to cheat him. Many are, but many more are not. Give's [Ezra] Pound's address. English publisher will submit plans and terms for distributing quarterly [This Quarter] in England. Clark had another breakdown. Note to Moorhead regarding paying someone to do work on magazine that Hemingway was doing for nothing. Verso of p.2 contains autograph memo, n.d., by Ethel Moorhead. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to Horace Liveright, 1925 May 11, TL copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:15)
    Mailed registered letter with signed contract and new story to replace story he was eliminating from In Our Time as censorable. There has been no acknowledgement or promised check. Would like note confirming that translations of his books are his property. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Horace] Liveright, 1925 June 21, TL copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:16)
    On anthology question, has referred permission to use two stories directly to Horace Liveright. Might help book to reprint stories. Leaving next week for Spain. Meeting Benchley there. Says he can grab off authors as fast as he can get them tight. He doesn't care about being published in anthology. All he wants is to have stuff published and be paid for it. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [1925 June 25], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. mounted. (Box-folder 3:17)
    [James] Joyce asked him when he should send his manuscript [new section of Finnegan's Wake] for This Quarter. Write Joyce care of Shakespeare and Company Bookstore. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], [ca. 1925 August], TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:18)
    Won't be a Spanish letter as working all the time on novel [The Sun Also Rises]. 68,000 words done. Going to be a swell novel with no autobiography and no complaints. In Our Time comes out the last of September with Boni & Liveright. May see him in Milan as he and Hadley going on walking tour through Tyrol and the Dolomites, and they may hop a train to see if Campari's can still put out a meal. Ready for a loaf when he gets book done. "Christ, how I've worked." Will put it away and not look at it until after Christmas, when he'll go over it, cut and fix it up and type it himself. Sending two photographs. Italians are worse crooks than the French, but the Milanese are the best of the Italians. Can't live in Italy because the political situation makes him so furious that he is upset and in trouble all the time. Discusses the murders of Matteoli. Promised himself he would not go to Italy again as long as the Fascists are in power. Discouraging to think that the country that produced Garibaldi should be ruled by that gang. As soon as Italy became a united nation it was finished. Poor old Cavour. 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to Ernest [Walsh], 1925 November 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:19)
    Sylvia Beach said Walsh wanted him to autograph In Our Time for him. He did so, but has not grace to do it properly. Had copies but all stolen or given away. Will try to find original Three Mountains edition for him. Just finished long fight story [Fifty Grand] that is damned good. They are about broke. Liveright book is getting splendid reviews. Mencken reviewed Three Mountains under "quackery" to confuse purchasers and do him as much damage as possible. Asks for proof of Undefeated. Had capable translation of Soldier's Home from Linati. Hemingway places great value on honest appreciation and only disgust from "bullshit." 6250-a
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to [Ethel] Moorhead and Ernest [Walsh], [1925] November 30, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:20)
    Returning corrected proof for The Undefeated. Four changes. Not just being like Joyce, wanting to rewrite story every time proof is sent. Going to Austria December 15. 6250-a
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Horace] Liveright, 1925 December 7, TL copy, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:21)
    Sending on the Mauretania manuscript of his new book, The Torrents of Spring. F. Scott Fitzgerald read and is very excited about it. This is not the long novel which he is calling The Sun Also Rises, which he is rewriting and working on all winter. Compares [The Torrents of Spring] to Fielding and Richardson. Bromfield read and said it was one of the funniest books he has ever read, and a very perfect American satire. Wishes he would get Ralph Barton to illustrate it. If he takes it, he has to push it. Has made no kick regarding lack of publicity for In Our Time. It should come out in the spring. Only reason he wouldn't publish it is for fear of offending Sherwood [Anderson]. If he takes book, wants $500 advance. Should ask for $1,000 as he can sell 20,000 copies. Funny books not to easy to get hold of. Those who have read Black Laughter will purchase. Cable him in Austria his decision on The Torrents of Spring. 6250-a
  - [Ernest Hemingway] to "Dear Editors,""> [early 1925?], AL fragment, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:22)
    Didn't know how they stood on money. He is not a rich man. They live on $1,000 a month. Gave up newspaper work at $125 to have freedom to write. He writes slowly, with difficulty, and his head must be clean to do it. Last year he made 1,1000 francs writing. Nothing in dollars. 6250-a